<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Applied by Design Blog</title>
		<description>Modern Application Development for the Aviation Industry</description>
		<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Mitigating Risk with Prototypes</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Central to an Applied by Design application solution is our development methodology.  We think it&amp;#39;s important to draw attention to not just&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;we think, but&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;we think as a company.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As organizations begin to dip their toes into the realm of modern browser-based applications, we believe it&amp;#39;s necessary to adopt a development methodology that embraces modern technology stacks while combating the common complexities and risks that manifest themselves in more traditional enterprise development projects.  At the center of our methodology is prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prototyping isn&amp;#39;t a new concept in application development, but there&amp;#39;s been a resurgence in attention to this approach being driven by recent thin client application development (browser-based applications).  Browser-based applications are built prevalently around open-source technology frameworks, and the pace of innovation in this space is phenomenal.  As these technologies mature, the pace of development itself has increased to a point where functional application prototypes are becoming less time consuming and are of higher fidelity, mitigating some of the immediate concerns with prototyping in the past.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our development methodology at Applied by Design has evolved to resemble a hybrid form of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rapid_application_development&quot;&gt;rapid application development&lt;/a&gt; that lends concepts from &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_Rapid_Development#Extreme_prototyping&quot;&gt;extreme prototyping&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_Rapid_Development#Evolutionary_prototyping&quot;&gt;evolutionary prototyping&lt;/a&gt;, and a healthy appreciation for &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development&quot;&gt;Test Driven Development (TDD)&lt;/a&gt;.  We&amp;#39;ll dive into the details of the methodology at a later date, but for now let&amp;#39;s focus on the concept of prototypes and why we use them at the core of our development process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/image/PrototypeDiagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our experience, extreme and evolutionary prototype concepts help promote an appropriate degree of systematic thinking during multiple stages of the project lifecycle.  It encourages both developers and business stakeholders to understand &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; decisions are being made, and it helps surface issues earlier in the application lifecycle.  The results are more actionable developer requirements, better stakeholder alignment, reduced long-term project risk, earlier user involvement, and more efficient application development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, we&amp;#39;ve witnessed high fidelity prototypes &lt;strong&gt;facilitate the communication of detailed requirements more efficiently&lt;/strong&gt; than the most robust set of traditional requirements artifacts.  We fully embrace user stories, use case scenarios, and strategy diagrams in our process, but we recognize that these are merely communication tools meant to align understanding and trace business needs to actionable development tasks.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Achieving a single common mental model in the minds of all project team members is difficult, and we&amp;#39;ve witnessed how the use of high fidelity prototypes can effectively break down the cognitive discrepancies that can exist between stakeholders.  Each person on a team may have a different image in their mind associated with a given set of written or verbal project requirements.  The role of the application prototype is simply to align each team member&amp;#39;s mental model on a single, common representation that all can see and agree on.  Until arriving at this stage, a team can never be truly confident that everyone&amp;#39;s speaking the same language.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of every project we engage in at Applied by Design is to arrive at this shared project understanding as fast as possible.  The prototype acts as the common ground where stakeholders can unite and spring off of into the next stage of development.  We think this concept is critical to the success of any development project.  &lt;strong&gt;We use prototyping at Applied by Design because it helps us build better applications, faster&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we work through our next application project, we&amp;#39;ll share more examples of prototyping in action.  We&amp;#39;re constantly evolving with changes in technology and with the industry itself, and as we mature we&amp;#39;ll be sharing what we learn along the way. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;///AxD&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 06:50:33 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/development/2013/09/10/mitigating-risk-with-prototypes.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/development/2013/09/10/mitigating-risk-with-prototypes.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Two Sides of the Same Coin</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Developing better airline applications for planning, operations and business strategy creates a better passenger experience.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relative to many other industries, airline planning and operations require a sophisticated and continually evolving toolset. Not only do technology changes like lighter, stronger aircraft materials, innovations in aircraft fuel and the leveraging of new online tools change the way airlines work, but fields supporting those tools, such as operations research, are continually improving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, designing modern, web based applications for airlines with a greater degree of system integration, sophistication and responsiveness can change the way an airline is able to operate. By adopting intelligent system designs and modern toolsets, airlines can make their business more efficient, responsive and profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it doesn&amp;#39;t stop there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more streamlined integration of the variety of data an airline is dealing with, along with the development of models to consume and analyze real time information suddenly puts new capabilities at the fingertips of not only the airline, but their customers. We live at a time when consumers are using incredibly sophisticated applications for everyday purposes: Social media, shopping and entainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These everyday apps are what your business application is being compared to. And in the fast paced, data rich airline indusrty, there is an untapped opportunity to provide a customer experience equal to the standard that customers expect in a digital environment. By bringing internal applications, data sources and analysis tools up to modern standards, airlines can also bring their customer into the loop, giving them the experience they expect from any other service, and should expect from the airlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An informed customer who feels in control of their experience and is allowed to understand the product they are purchasing is a customer who will leave satisfied, even when the unexpected happens. The customer experience can be a continuous and participatory one, from planning a trip, to the airport, to the flight, to once they&amp;#39;re back home and, especially, when an itinerary doesn&amp;#39;t go as planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applied by Design thinks it&amp;#39;s time to focus on building products for the airlines that help solve problems for both the business as well as their passengers. There are vast opportunities for airlines to do business smarter, more efficiently, and in a way that looks out for the bottom line and the customer at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do so, an airline needs to start by rethinking both how it designs and uses its own internal tools as well as what it means to connect and engage with its customers.  It demands an attention to detail, to progressive design thinking,a multi-diciplinary understanding of the tools needed to run an airline, and an unwavering focus on every aspect of the customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;///AxD&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 11:51:33 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/design/2013/09/01/two-sides-of-the-same-coin.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/design/2013/09/01/two-sides-of-the-same-coin.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>What We're Up To</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here at Applied by Design we&amp;#39;re working to put the right tools in the hands of aviation industry decision makers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we&amp;#39;re at it we&amp;#39;ll be using this space to post our vision of where we&amp;#39;re going next. Check out the rest of the site to learn more, and follow us via your favorite outlet (Twitter, LinkedIn, Google+) to keep up with the latest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AppliedByDesign&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linkedin.com/company/applied-by-design&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;///AxD&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 11:51:33 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/2013/08/30/what-were-up-to.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/2013/08/30/what-were-up-to.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>