<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Applied by Design Blog</title>
		<description>Modern Application Development for the Aviation Industry</description>
		<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Hybrid Consulting</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;We offer an argument for calculated and diligent solution design, within the framework of the user population, organization and firm. This requires a new perspective on how applications are designed;  a perspective that compliments the power and agility of the new world of web application development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Today&amp;#39;s Environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arena for building web applications to support today’s business has changed. Modern web application tools make it possible for agile development cycles that take a fraction of the time of traditional processes and create lightweight, responsive solutions. This is especially true in technology industries where firms are increasingly using web applications for mission critical analysis, testing and customer engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is the ability for business teams to own much of the development process, especially in organizations already invested in technology focused skill sets.  In this environment, point solutions can be quickly developed to meet niche needs throughout the organization. While the organization can leverage this situation through the quick development of responsive solutions, it also &lt;strong&gt;requires a new look at how business solutions are fit into a greater organizational strategy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A call to anchor development in organization strategy is not an argument against agile development. This is an argument for calculated and diligent solution design, within the framework of the user population, organization and firm. This requires a new perspective on how applications are designed; a perspective that compliments the power and agility of the new world of web application development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This perspective can be achieved with a hybrid of traditional, strategically oriented services with the operational and tactical activities required to actually develop a solution: &lt;strong&gt;A new independent, highly focused, multi-disciplinary style of consulting service&lt;/strong&gt;. A service that provides the strategic orientation and alignment needed to manage quickly evolving tools with the technical and engineering domain knowledge and creative design expertise to actually execute on an application development project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/image/hybrid-consulting.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Part Management Consulting Firm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It begins with an appreciation and understanding of strategic alignment tools traditionally associated with management consulting. With an ever increasing set of solutions within an organization, strategic planning is required to influence how tactical development decisions are being made. 
Additionally, as solutions are continually being developed outside of traditional, legacy IT paths, an organization’s &lt;strong&gt;portfolio of solutions must be strategically balanced&lt;/strong&gt; to deliver the best solution for the customer and shareholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside is that often traditional services fall short of delivering actionable, operational level tools from which development projects can work. Due to a lack of domain knowledge and development experience, management consulting often cannot trace strategic needs all of the way to meaningful, actionable, operational application requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Part Application Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To remedy this, a rich understanding of the tools available today for both model and data development, as well as expertise in user interface and user experience design is needed. At the end of the day, application projects are building &lt;strong&gt;a technical solution to a business problem&lt;/strong&gt;. Developers, either internal or external to the business, deliver the lines of code that make a concept a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside is that, as projects and requirements evolve, developers can often become detached from the needs of both the end user population as well as the organization. This is especially true as applications are being deployed to a diverse set of users, from analysts to CEOs, and to a variety of organizations, both internal and external. Additionally, as more technology companies begin to rely on these solutions, developers have less knowledge of the sophisticated modeling techniques needed to support analysis and data model design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Applied by Design Bridges the Gap&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is &lt;strong&gt;a hybrid of strategic, development and design thinking&lt;/strong&gt; to deliver the tools and processes you need to make your development project work. 
In this mode of thinking, strategic needs driven by organization, customer and shareholder requirements can, through the use of the appropriate tools and frameworks, be traced into actionable steps in an application development program. User experience and user interface can be developed with an understanding of both the opportunities and limitations that might exist with respect to the users, as well as the models and data at hand. Analytical processes can be customized to fit the organization and firm, and can be designed in such a way to evolve and leverage future capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our philosophy at Applied by Design. By &lt;strong&gt;combining domain knowledge and technical understanding with the ability to develop and execute&lt;/strong&gt; on strategic planning tools, we believe a greater solution can be delivered to an organization; one that exceeds the expectations of its users, creates value for the organization, is designed to evolve within the organization’s application portfolio as well as within the application development environment at large, and one that delivers for the organization’s customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;///AxD&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2013 03:49:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/consulting/2013/09/24/hybrid-consulting.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/consulting/2013/09/24/hybrid-consulting.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Analytical User Personas</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ve discussed how we use &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/development/2013/09/10/mitigating-risk-with-prototypes.html&quot;&gt;rapid prototyping&lt;/a&gt; at Applied by Design and its ability to align stakeholder&amp;#39;s mental models of a system. User personas serve a similar purpose in delivering shared understanding of the intended end-user.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User personas play a key role in our approach to user-centered design.  They attempt to bucket common traits, behavioral tendencies, and properties of a target audience into a subset of generalized archetypes.  Instead of designing an application to meet the needs of 100 different users, a detailed persona seeks to generalize the subset of users you&amp;#39;re specifically targeting with your solution.  Your team can then focus on the needs of a single user who represents the needs and wants of the greater target audience.  That&amp;#39;s the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll admit, user personas can be pretty fluffy.  The trick for us was to add our own modern spin on the artifact of a persona to better support and resonate with our design process.  What we were looking for was something with less &amp;#39;fluff&amp;#39; and more of an analytical basis as our customers are often engineering or technical teams.  We ended up taking more of an infographic approach to the user persona.  Here&amp;#39;s a peek at a sample we put together.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ![image](/image/Analytical-User-Persona.png) --&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-center&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/image/Analytical-User-Persona.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;blue-text&quot;&gt;Blue information&lt;/span&gt; is for this specific persona (Ben, Aviation Analyst).  &lt;span class=&quot;orange-text&quot;&gt;Orange information&lt;/span&gt; references the aggregate set of personas for a given team or project (there are 3 personas that represent the 25 team members in this example).  Let&amp;#39;s break some of it down by section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;1. Persona Bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our example, we&amp;#39;re helping a team of 25 employees build an application solution to facilitate their daily operations.  This persona represents one-third of the target users for the intended application.  We gather the information from user interviews and surveys statistics, and find that this group has, on average, multiple degrees and came from the airline industry prior to their current job.  In their current role, they&amp;#39;re generally aviation analysts with 10-15 years of professional experience.  Calling this persona &amp;#39;Ben&amp;#39; humanizes the archetype to make it easier to identify with and recall later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/image/bio-header.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;2. Technology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re building an application solution, so we need to get a grasp on the segment&amp;#39;s comfort level with technology.  We can ask questions about their internet usage, breaking it down into subcomponents and drilling deeper into specific preferences for browser technology and email clients.  On a weekly basis, this group spends 4 hours checking email &lt;span class=&quot;blue-text&quot;&gt;(blue bar)&lt;/span&gt;, which is fairly consistent with the broader group of aggregate personas &lt;span class=&quot;orange-text&quot;&gt;(orange bar)&lt;/span&gt;.  General browsing indicates that this group spends ~60% more time per week than the team average casually engaging with the internet, and they&amp;#39;re fragmented among browers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/image/technology.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;3. Skills &amp;amp; Expertise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding a segment&amp;#39;s areas of expertise allows us to identify the application design considerations that might be most influenced by specific groups.  For example, this graphic indicates that the the &amp;quot;Ben&amp;#39;s&amp;quot; more often self-identify themselves as experts in data analytics and data visualization compared with their peers.  Conversely, they&amp;#39;re less comfortable in financial analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/image/expertise.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get the point.  Each section should have an intended purpose.  The set of questions and attributes collected in a persona will vary with the project and the team, but the concept is still the same.  Personas typically don&amp;#39;t take this type of analytical approach, but we think a healthy appreciation for the data driving them can help instill a sense of confidence and trust in the messages they&amp;#39;re conveying.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, the persona is customized for the specific application. This artifact ultimately informs operational level requirements ranging from UI/UX considerations to the level of detail and interactivity of the analytical engines themselves. By anchoring all downstream requirements on these conceptual views of the end user, project decisions become traceable to a common, agreed upon model of the user. This is of value not only at the inception of the project, but throughout, and should be used as a touchstone for operational as well as tactical decisions as the application evolves. Our persona process provides an artifact that isn&amp;#39;t just a onetime exercise, but is an actionable document that acts as a reference throughout the life of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;///AxD&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 03:45:33 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/design/2013/09/17/analytical-user-personas.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/design/2013/09/17/analytical-user-personas.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Mitigating Risk with Prototypes</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Central to an Applied by Design application solution is our development methodology. We think it&amp;#39;s important to draw attention to not just &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; we think, but &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we think as a company.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As organizations begin to dip their toes into the realm of modern browser-based applications, we believe it&amp;#39;s necessary to adopt a development methodology that embraces modern technology stacks while combating the common complexities and risks that manifest themselves in more traditional enterprise development projects.  At the center of our methodology is prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prototyping isn&amp;#39;t a new concept in application development, but there&amp;#39;s been a resurgence in attention to this approach being driven by recent thin client application development (browser-based applications).  Browser-based applications are built prevalently around open-source technology frameworks, and the pace of innovation in this space is phenomenal.  As these technologies mature, the pace of development itself has increased to a point where functional application prototypes are becoming less time consuming and are of higher fidelity, mitigating some of the immediate concerns with prototyping in the past.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our development methodology at Applied by Design has evolved to resemble a hybrid form of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rapid_application_development&quot;&gt;rapid application development&lt;/a&gt; that lends concepts from &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_Rapid_Development#Extreme_prototyping&quot;&gt;extreme prototyping&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_Rapid_Development#Evolutionary_prototyping&quot;&gt;evolutionary prototyping&lt;/a&gt;, and a healthy appreciation for &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development&quot;&gt;Test Driven Development (TDD)&lt;/a&gt;.  We&amp;#39;ll dive into the details of the methodology at a later date, but for now let&amp;#39;s focus on the concept of prototypes and why we use them at the core of our development process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/image/PrototypeDiagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our experience, extreme and evolutionary prototype concepts help promote an appropriate degree of systematic thinking during multiple stages of the project lifecycle.  It encourages both developers and business stakeholders to understand &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; decisions are being made, and it helps surface issues earlier in the application lifecycle.  The results are more actionable developer requirements, better stakeholder alignment, reduced long-term project risk, earlier user involvement, and more efficient application development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, we&amp;#39;ve witnessed how high fidelity prototypes can &lt;strong&gt;facilitate the communication of detailed requirements more efficiently&lt;/strong&gt; than the most robust set of traditional requirements artifacts.  We fully embrace user stories, use case scenarios, and strategy diagrams in our process, but we recognize that these are merely communication tools meant to align understanding and trace business needs to actionable development tasks.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Achieving a single common mental model in the minds of all project team members is difficult, and an effective prototype can serve to break down the cognitive discrepancies that exist between stakeholders.  Each person on a team may have a different image in their mind associated with a given set of written or verbal project requirements.  The role of the application prototype is simply to align each team member&amp;#39;s mental model on a single, common representation that all can see and agree on.  Until arriving at this stage, a team can never be truly confident that everyone&amp;#39;s speaking the same language.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of every project we engage in at Applied by Design is to arrive at this shared project understanding as fast as possible.  The prototype acts as the common ground where stakeholders can unite and spring off of into the next stage of development.  We think this concept is critical to the success of any development project.  &lt;strong&gt;We use prototyping at Applied by Design because it helps us build better applications, faster&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we work through our next application project, we&amp;#39;ll share more examples of prototyping in action.  We&amp;#39;re constantly evolving with changes in technology and with the industry itself, and as we mature we&amp;#39;ll be sharing what we learn along the way. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;///AxD&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 06:50:33 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/development/2013/09/10/mitigating-risk-with-prototypes.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/development/2013/09/10/mitigating-risk-with-prototypes.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Two Sides of the Same Coin</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Developing better airline applications for planning, operations and business strategy creates a better passenger experience.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relative to many other industries, airline planning and operations require a sophisticated and continually evolving toolset. Not only do technology changes like lighter, stronger aircraft materials, innovations in aircraft fuel and the leveraging of new online tools change the way airlines work, but fields supporting those tools, such as operations research, are continually improving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, designing modern, web based applications for airlines with a greater degree of system integration, sophistication and responsiveness can change the way an airline is able to operate. By adopting intelligent system designs and modern toolsets, airlines can make their business more efficient, responsive and profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it doesn&amp;#39;t stop there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more streamlined integration of the variety of data an airline is dealing with, along with the development of models to consume and analyze real time information suddenly puts new capabilities at the fingertips of not only the airline, but their customers. We live at a time when consumers are using incredibly sophisticated applications for everyday purposes: Social media, shopping and entainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These everyday apps are what your business application is being compared to. And in the fast paced, data rich airline indusrty, there is an untapped opportunity to provide a customer experience equal to the standard that customers expect in a digital environment. By bringing internal applications, data sources and analysis tools up to modern standards, airlines can also bring their customer into the loop, giving them the experience they expect from any other service, and should expect from the airlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An informed customer who feels in control of their experience and is allowed to understand the product they are purchasing is a customer who will leave satisfied, even when the unexpected happens. The customer experience can be a continuous and participatory one, from planning a trip, to the airport, to the flight, to once they&amp;#39;re back home and, especially, when an itinerary doesn&amp;#39;t go as planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applied by Design thinks it&amp;#39;s time to focus on building products for the airlines that help solve problems for both the business as well as their passengers. There are vast opportunities for airlines to do business smarter, more efficiently, and in a way that looks out for the bottom line and the customer at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do so, an airline needs to start by rethinking both how it designs and uses its own internal tools as well as what it means to connect and engage with its customers.  It demands an attention to detail, to progressive design thinking,a multi-diciplinary understanding of the tools needed to run an airline, and an unwavering focus on every aspect of the customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;///AxD&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 11:51:33 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/design/2013/09/01/two-sides-of-the-same-coin.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/design/2013/09/01/two-sides-of-the-same-coin.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>What We're Up To</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Here at Applied by Design we&amp;#39;re working to put the right tools in the hands of aviation industry decision makers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we&amp;#39;re at it we&amp;#39;ll be using this space to post our vision of where we&amp;#39;re going next. Check out the rest of the site to learn more, and follow us via your favorite outlet (Twitter, LinkedIn, Google+) to keep up with the latest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AppliedByDesign&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linkedin.com/company/applied-by-design&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;///AxD&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 11:51:33 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/2013/08/30/what-were-up-to.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.appliedbydesign.com/2013/08/30/what-were-up-to.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>